Finding Aid for the Frantisek W. Galan Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Frantisek W. Galan Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0164
2.5 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Dr. Frantisek W. Galan was a Professor of Comparative Literature and Slavic Languages and Literatures, as well as the Director of the Program in Comparative Literature, and a Professor of English at Vanderbilt University from 1989 until his death in 1992. A native of Ontario, Canada, and a person of Czechoslovakian descent, Galan pursued an active academic and professional career in Comparative Literatures and Russian.
Dr. Galan earned his undergraduate degree in English from the University of Toronto in 1970, and went on to complete his Master’s Degree in Comparative Literature at Princeton University at 1974 and his PhD in Comparative Literature and Slavic Languages at the University of Toronto in 1980. From 1987 to 1989, Galan worked as an associate English professor at the Georgia Institute of technology, teaching both English survey and seminar classes. However, in 1989 Galan accepted a position as a Professor of Comparative Literature and Slavic Languages at Vanderbilt University. While at Vanderbilt, Galan served as an undergraduate academic advisor and sat on two graduate dissertation committees. A committed instructor and intellectual scholar, Galan continued his service by assuming a leadership position as the Director of Vanderbilt’s Program in Comparative Literatures.
Throughout his research and scholarly endeavors, Galan conducted extensive research, taught undergraduate students, and published. One of Galan’s early and most significant article publications was centered on the controversial yet pioneering contributions of Prague philosopher and literary scientist, Valclav Cerny in ARDIS, the Journal of Russian Literature in 1974. During his academic tenure as a German and Slavic Languages faculty member, Galan received a series of fellowships and grants, including a Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship from Cornell University, providing Galan with the opportunity to perform a linguistic analysis of a “Fonetika, Fonologia, and Grafika.” Galan’s linguistic analysis of “Fonetika, Fonologia, and Grafika” allowed him to delve into and examine the verbal tenses and grammatical nuances of twentieth century literary theory.
Dr. Galan passed away in 1992, just shortly after he assumed leadership over Vanderbilt’s Program in Comparative Literature.
Scope and Content Note
The Frantisek W. Galan Collection contains a series of Galan’s undergraduate and graduate school syllabi, personal notes, graded academic materials, various newspaper clippings, excerpts from his research projects, as well as student projects and evaluations. The majority of the Frantisek W. Galan Collection pertains directly to Galan’s academic career at Princeton University from the years 1971 to 1974.
- Undergraduate Materials
  - Academic Career—B.A., University of Toronto—Course Materials, Syllabi, and Personal Notes, 1967-1970
    - Outgoing Correspondence—from Galan to Mr. Proffer, (1974) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Incoming Correspondence—From Rene Wellek to Galan, (1975) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fall, 1967—University of Toronto, English 440: Department of Fine Arts (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - English 440 Course Syllabus (Box 1)
      - Poetry and Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
      - Personal notes written on four index cards (Box 1)
      - Two written and graded assignments (Box 1)
    - University of Toronto, Academic Career, Poetry and Notes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Excerpt from book, Beckett Translating Beckett: Comment C’est: 201 (Box 1)
      - Excerpt from Shakespeare: Sonnet 87 (Box 1)
      - Poetry excerpts written in Russian (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
    - 1968—Galan, Canadian Immigration Identification Card and Citizenship Documents, (October 15, 1968) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - University of Toronto, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Russian excerpts from unknown texts (Box 1)
      - Personal notes written in Russian, hand written (Box 1)
      - Graded Russian essay assignments (Box 1)
    - Fall 1969, University of Toronto, Philosophy 400: Aesthetics, Department of Philosophy Fine Arts (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Philosophy 400 Course Syllabus (Box 1)
      - Course Assignments/Essay Prompt (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
    - University of Toronto, English 460 Annual Examinations, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Annual Exam—Written, Directions and Prompts (Box 1)
      - Annual Exam—Oral, Directions (Box 1)
      - Personal notes, ‘criticism of major texts’ (Box 1)
      - Book excerpts, unknown (Box 1)
    - Fall-Spring, 1969-1970—University of Toronto, Slavic Languages, Course Syllabi and Reading Lists (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Slavic 420—1st year Russian (Box 1)
      - Slavic 422—4th year Russian (Box 1)
      - Exercise in Russian Syntax PII (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970, University of Toronto, Department of English, English 439 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - English 439 List of Topics for Consideration (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
      - Graded Essay, “About Playwrights and What They Have to Say” (Box 1)
      - Graded Essay, “A Human Being, A Human Personality” (Box 1)
    - 1970, Slavic Studies 426, Department of Slavic Languages and Literature (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Annual Examinations Directions and Prompts (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
      - Graded Essay, “Olesha: A Writer Who Wanted to Write Everyday (And Could Only Envy) (Box 1)
      - Book Excerpt: Alexander Solzhenitsyn, Matryona’s Home (Box 1)
    - University of Toronto Bulletins, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1970, University of Toronto, Philosophy of Religion: 414 & Philosophy 203 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Essay Topics, Philosophy 414 (Box 1)
      - Essay Topics, Philosophy 203 (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 1)
      - Philosophy 203 First Term Exam (Box 1)
      - Magazine clippings, unknown (Box 1)
      - Essay written by Galan, On the Actuality of the Rational and the Rationality of the Actual: In Celebration of the Hegel Bicentenary (Box 1)
      - Essay, written by Young Kun Kim (Herbert H, Lehman College) “Master and Servant in Hegel” (Box 1)
    - University of Toronto, Philosophy: 342, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Russian highlighted newspaper clippings (Box 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written on H.L. Hart—Law, Liberty, and Morality (Box 1)
      - Three graded philosophy essays (Box 1)
      - Two political cartoons (Box 1)
- Academic Career, 1970-1972
  - Academic Career, University of Toronto & Princeton University—Slavic Languages and Comparative Literatures (Box 2)
  - Academic Career—Collected material by date
    - University of Toronto, Department of Slavic Languages & Literature Russian Essays, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Russian Poetry (Box 2)
      - Russian Homework Assignments (Box 2)
    - University of Toronto, Department of Slavic Languages & Literatures Slavic 432: Russian Poetry Syllabus, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Russian Essays (Box 2)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
      - Slavic 432, Annual Examination (Box 2)
    - University of Toronto, Russian Literature Russian Poetry, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Personal Notes (Box 2)
      - Typed notes on Doctor Zhivago (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Provisional Syllabus for Modern German Literary Theory (Box 2)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, Package from “Dean of Student Affairs” for the Program in Comparative Literature, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Graduate Program Requirements (Box 2)
      - Comprehensive Reading List (Box 2)
      - References for the Study of Comparative Literature (Box 2)
      - General Examination Guidelines (Box 2)
      - Dissertation and Final Public Oral Examination Guidelines (Box 2)
      - Unknown Book Excerpts (Box 2)
      - Types Essay Assignments (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, Russian Literature, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
      - Typed essay, Chekhov (Box 2)
      - Preceptorials List, Spring, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Russian Book Excerpts (Box 2)
    - 1971, Princeton University (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Official Register—Course Offerings, (February 1971- June 1971) (Box 2)
      - Temporary Bus Schedule, January 1970 (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature. Studies in Criticism II: From Lessing to Valery—C.L. 526, Fall, 1971 & Spring, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Comparative Literature 526 Syllabus (Box 2)
      - Comparative Literature Selective Bibliography (Box 2)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
      - Typed Notes: Longinus, Peri Hupsous, and Criticism (Box 2)
    - Spring 1971-1972—Princeton University, Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures & Program in Comparative Literatures (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - European Literature 319 Syllabus (Box 2)
      - European Literature 319 Bibliography (Box 2)
      - Comparative Literatures 551: Topics in the Study of Literacy Genre, 14th cen. Allegory (Box 2)
      - History 358: Chronological List of Dates (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Comparative Literature 527: European Novel, I Syllabus (Box 2)
      - Reading List for C.L. 527 (Box 2)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 2)
      - Book Excerpt, Richardson and Fieldling (Box 2)
- Master’s Degree Materials
  - Academic Career—Collected material by date (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Comparative Literature 521: Literary Interpretations (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 3)
      - List of Suggested Topics for Comparative Literature 526 (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, Spring 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Comparative Language 551: Seminar: Special Topics in Lyrical Poetry—Rilke and Stevens, Syllabus (Box 3)
    - Comparative Literature 528: History of the Modern Novel, II, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Comparative Literature 523-24 Course Syllabus, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Comparative Literature 528 Course Syllabus, Spring, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes (Box 3)
      - Selective Bibliography (Box 3)
      - Reading excerpt—“Richardson and Fielding, Frank Kermode” (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Humanistic Studies 404, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Humanistic Studies: 404, Contemporary Greek Poetry in Translation. Senior Seminar (Box 3)
      - C.P. Cavafy: Selected Poems (Box 3)
      - New York Times Review Clippings on Greek Poets (Class Related) (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Comparative Literature 523-524: The Classical Tradition I and II (Box 3)
      - Comparative Literature Documents (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Comparative Literature 525-526: Studies in Criticism I and II (Box 3)
      - Studies in Criticism I: Classicism and Neo-Classicism (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, Fall, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Comparative Literature 521: The Comparative Study of Poetry – “Metaphysical Poetry” and Background, Princeton University (Box 3)
      - Reserve Bibliography (Box 3)
      - Poetry Excerpts—From Various Texts/Sources (Unknown) (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Russian poetry, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Russian Poems, unknown (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Poetry, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Poetry excerpts (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, Fall, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Comparative Literature 527: Studies in Literary History I: Dostoevsky and European Literature (Box 3)
      - Comparative Literature 527, Bibliography (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, Spring, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Comparative Literature 528, Seminar Syllabus (Box 3)
      - Poetry Excerpts, typed (sources unknown) (Box 3)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 3)
    - Princeton University, Program in Comparative Literature, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Selective Bibliographies (Box 3)
- Academic Materials
  - Academic Career, Princeton University & Writing Materials on V. Cerney (Box 4)
  - Academic Career—Collected material by date (Box 4)
    - Professional Career, “Fonetika, Fonologia & Grafika” (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 4)
    - 1974, Princeton University, Russian Poetry (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Poetry excerpts written in Russian (Box 4)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 4)
    - Princeton University, Russian Poetry and Notes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Poetry excerpts written in Russian (Box 4)
      - Poetry analysis (Box 4)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 4)
    - Touchstone, The Magazine of the Tennessee Humanities Council, Catherine The Great, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet from Art Exhibit, University of Toronto – “Guderna Pamphlet”, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Writings—Articles, Research, and Translations (Box 4)
    - Book Excerpts, Research Materials (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - “Cesk Literatura”, (1966) (Box 4)
      - “Ceskoslovenska Rusistika”, (1968) (Box 4)
    - Book Excerpts, Research Materials (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - – Valclav Cerney – “Nase Nove Barokisticke Publikace”, (1969) (Box 4)
    - Vaclav Cerny—CV and Obituary, Note Cards with Reference to Renee Welek (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Articles Pertaining to Vaclav Cerny—Written in Czech, (Dates—1927, 1929, 1935, and 1947) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Galan’s Research on Vaclav Cerny’s “Dostoevsky and His Devils” (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Personal Notes, hand written (Box 4)
    - Galan’s Translation of Vaclav Cerny’s “Dostoevsky and His Devils” (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Galan’s Personal Notes & Articles excerpts on—Roszhovor s Vaclavem Cernym (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Galan’s Contract with Ardis Publishers—For writing on V. Cerney’s, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Memorandum of Agreement (Box 4)
      - Letter correspondences from Ardis Publishers (Box 4)
      - Translated excerpts, typed (Box 4)
- Professional Materials
  - Student Evaluations (Box 5)
    - Galan—Student Evaluation for English 100201 – for, April 18, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Enclosed letter from Georgia Institute of Technology (Box 5)
      - Item Response Distribution—Professor Report, Winter Quarter, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Completed Scranton sheets with student names (Box 5)
    - Galan—Professional Career, Student Evaluations: English 313A –for, April 18, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Georgia Institute of technology (Box 5)
  - Vanderbilt Dissertation Committees (Box 5)
    - Professional Career at Vanderbilt—Dissertation of Edwin C. Gentzler (Chapter 1), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Professional Career at Vanderbilt—Dissertation of Edwin C. Gentzler. (Chapter 2), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Professional Career at Vanderbilt—Dissertation chapter of unknown student (Chapter unknown), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Professional Career at Vanderbilt—Dissertation chapter of unknown student (Chapter unknown), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Professional Career (Box 5)
    - Vanderbilt University Computer information documents, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Log-in/user names (Box 5)
      - Printing bill statements (Box 5)
      - Computer finance plans (Box 5)
    - Writing samples from undergraduate students, two classes, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Fiction into Film (Box 5)
      - Humanities 205 (Box 5)